28. The Pygmalion Effect. You get what you expect. That's the Pygmalion
effect in a nutshell. Studies show that people tend to live up to, or down to, the expectations
people place on them. Our reality really is influenced by the opinions
and expectations of others. When other people expect us to be great, we are more likely
to be great. When we aren't expected to perform well, we usually won't bother. It
is amazing how affected we are by the labels people attach to us. Many studies have demonstrated
the Pygmalion effect. One study, by Robert Rosenthal and Lenore Jacobson, randomly selected
students in several classrooms. Teachers were told that these students were especially smart.
The teachers, therefore, expected high performance from these students, and they got it. At the
end of the year, the randomly selected students had increased their IQs and performed better
overall than the rest, even though they were actually no better or smarter than the rest
of the class. Their teachers had believed that they had great potential, and that had
caused the potential to appear. There is a downside to the Pygmalion Effect,
of course. Just as we rise to meet high expectations, we may be knocked down by low expectations.
Jane Elliott conducted a famous test on school children. She divided them by eye color, blue
versus brown. One day, the blue-eyed group was praised, while those with brown eyes were
told they were inferior. The next day, the roles were reversed. Students took spelling
tests on both days. Most students did very badly on the day they were made to feel inferior.
Labels can create reality. People who are expected to fail often fail. People who are
labeled as winners generally win. If you want to get the best from yourself, expect it.